All right.
Welcome, everyone, to CS
25, I believe week eight.
Today, we are very excited
to have Eshed Margalit, who
is a neuroscientist and
ML researcher, working
to understand biological
systems with AI.
He completed his PhD in
neuroscience here at Stanford,
where he constructed
self-supervised neural networks
that incorporate biologically
inspired constraints
to explain the structure,
function, and development
of primary visual cortex.
He's currently an ML
scientist at Noetik,
AI native biotech startup
focused on curing cancer.
And his work, he develops novel
transformer model architectures
and tasks that learn from
large, multi-modal data
sets of patient tumor
biology and applies
these models to drug discovery.
As a reminder, please fill
out the attendance form.
And if you're online, you can
ask any questions on Slido.
With that, I'll let--
you should take it away.
Awesome.
Thank you for that introduction.
I feel like that covered it all.
So we're done here.
We can wrap it up.
I'm going to talk today
about a mix of basic ML ideas
about how to do
multimodal learning,
and a little bit of
the kind of research
we're doing at Noetik
where I work now.
I'm going to talk
really in three parts.
You can tell I'm fond
of alliteration here.
I'll do multimodal model
madness and tell you
a little bit about ideas for
incorporating information
streams from
multiple modalities.
Then I'll focus more
specifically on cancer.
So in that first
part, if you're not
interested in biology
or cancer, one,
I'll convince you otherwise.
And two, you'll get a lot out
of that first part, I hope.
And then I have a
few random things
I threw in at the end
about work in progress
that might be exciting.
So just to put it out there, my
assumptions about this audience
are that you're interested in
research on transformers, given
the course title, and
specifically maybe
novel transformer
architectures that you
haven't encountered before.
I'll assume that you're curious
about how we're actually
trying to use transformers
outside of an academic context,
and to bring it into a
clinically useful context.
I will assume that you're kind
of familiar with the basics
of transformers in
machine learning,
but not necessarily experts.
There will be no pop quiz
about equations or formulas
or architecture diagrams today.
And I will assume that you don't
have any familiarity with cancer
immunology, so
this will hopefully
be friendly to people that
have never really thought
about that world,
but I hope you all
agree that curing cancer is
a worthwhile thing to do,
and I'll tell you about
the ways we're trying
to bring these worlds together.
What you should know about me.
This was covered a
bit in the intro,
but I did my PhD here at
Stanford in neuroscience,
so I'm actually not
a cancer immunologist
by training or background.
I'm new to that field.
My background is in
computational neuroscience,
and specifically
visual cortex and how
the primate visual system works.
And when I was here,
I mostly studied
how we can build in biological
constraints into, at the time,
convolutional neural networks
to make them more brain like.
And my broad interest
is in understanding
how complex biological
systems get put together,
how they work when
they're working,
and how they don't work
when they stop working.
Before I go further, I should
call out the other people
that I work with at Noetik.
We're a pretty small machine
learning research team,
but the stuff I'm
going to show you today
is due to their efforts
as much as mine.
And I'll do my best
to call out when they
contributed specific things.
But in case I forget, these
are their names and faces.
And the last bit
of housekeeping.
This is my plan for
roughly the next hour.
I might try to go a
little faster to save time
for questions at the end.
I'm going to try to
convince you, primarily,
that there's a lot of really
exciting and creative work
to be done in multimodal
machine learning, especially
with transformers.
And two, something that I became
convinced of in the past year
and a half, really, that
cancer biology is just
a really fantastic place to
do that kind of research.
The kind of data we're
generating is really unique,
and something that I wouldn't
have considered as a substrate
to do basic ML research.
For bonus points, I'll
also try to convince you
that we're actually
making progress on drug
discovery for cancer at Noetik.
And then, the way
that I normally
prefer to give
presentations is I'm
super happy to have
clarifying questions.
So please, if something
doesn't make sense,
it's probably I forgot a
sentence or a definition.
Do let me know.
If you have larger philosophical
questions about why we're all
here, I'd also love
to talk about those,
but I'll try to save a little
time at the end for the more
freewheeling discussion.
OK.
So with that said, let me jump
into my conceptual framework
for thinking about
multimodal model madness.
I think a unifying goal for much
of AI, I won't say all of AI,
but much of it is to
build world models.
And by that, I
mean a system that
can simulate the future
state of the world,
conditioned on observations of
the current state of the world,
and also being able
to simulate forward
the effects that system's
actions will have on the future.
So this necessarily means
you have the reality that
is out there, you have sensors
that collect information
about that reality, you perceive
it with your world model,
and ideally, you're able
to run a simulation of,
OK, well, if I take this
action, how will the world
change in the future?
And that is a very powerful
and generic framework
for being able to reason about
why the world is the way it
is, how you should act.
It obviously plays into
planning and perception.
So one thing that
I think is obvious
is that the world is
perceived, at least by us,
and the world models in our
heads in a multimodal way.
So you have visual modality
that will tell you, for example,
that this roundabout that
I biked through many times
on my way to lab is very
dangerous and chaotic when
people are running late
to class and panicking.
But you're not just getting
the visual information,
you, of course, also
have the audio modality,
which comes from a different
sensor, a microphone
for a machine or ears for us,
and you get an audio stream.
And often when you encounter
video or image data,
you could also have a
text representation.
Someone might have
written a caption
under their video saying,
whoa, this roundabout
is extremely chaotic and I'm
going to try to avoid it.
My thesis, or my assumption
is that the best world models
are going to be
able to incorporate
all of these modalities
and make decisions
about what to do based, not just
on one of them, but all of them
in a productive way.
So when you're running the world
model in your head, where you're
perceiving the data from
all these modalities,
you might have a
question like, what
will happen if I start walking
forward into this roundabout?
And because you
have the combination
of maybe someone warned
you ahead of time,
you can hear what's going
on, can see what's going on,
you're able to predict
that you might get crashed
into by-- somebody on a bike
who's running late for class.
The task of that model is
effectively multimodal learning.
You need to know
how to integrate
these various information
streams, which natively come
in many different
formats, and you
need to learn from them
in a way that gives you
the best chance of making
accurate simulations of what's
going to happen in the world.
I want to make a distinction
that I think is important
and will come up a couple
of times in this talk,
about two reasons you
might care about combining
multimodal streams.
One of them is the idea that
you could do multimodality
as translation.
You could say,
there's information
in the visual domain, there's
information in the audio domain,
and what I want to do is have
a representation of the world
that merges those
things so that I've
captured all of the
information about one
modality in the other modality.
The other thing that you might
want to do is disambiguation.
So there could be
information that just is not
available in one modality.
And So you have a blind spot,
both figuratively and literally
here, where if you
only had a camera,
you wouldn't know everything
about the state of the world,
and you're going to need to
incorporate this other modality
to get a full picture
of what is happening
in the world around you.
So I'll try to talk a little
bit as I'm giving examples
in the literature and in
our work about whether I
think we're doing translation
or disambiguation.
So translation has a
very familiar shape.
It's about capturing all
of the information in one
modality and another modality.
So when you're
building, for example,
a text to image
system, what you want
is for all of the
information in the prompt
that you're sending
to the system
to be reflected in the image.
You want to basically
push these things together
so that when I include a bit of
information in the text stream,
I want it reflected back
to me in the image stream.
And when I talk about
disambiguation, what I mean
is that you need
to piece together
information that is only
going to be available in one
modality or another.
So for example, let's say
you're approaching this building
and you see everyone
sprinting out of it.
Now, there's some
ambiguity here.
There are actually many reasons
why people could be running out
of the building.
Now, if you combine that
with your sense of hearing,
you might hear that there is
a fire alarm going off inside,
and that rapidly disambiguates
which state of the world
you're in, that there's a fire
and everyone's running away
from it.
But you could also have
a second scenario where
you hear an announcement
that there's
free boba for the first 10
students that get to it,
and now everyone is sprinting
out of the building,
and your world
model should update.
If you want boba, you
need to turn around and go
one direction, maybe to
where the announcement is
saying to go.
If there's a fire, you head
to the nearest evacuation
point or whatever
it is we're all
supposed to do if that happens.
OK, the next few slides will be
a tour that I will acknowledge
is both brief and
incomplete, about how
people have tried to
incorporate multimodal streams
in the literature.
And I'm really going to
go over five things here.
You don't have to
memorize them now.
I'll go through them one by one.
But one thing that
I want to call out
is, when people talk about
multimodality or merging streams
from one modality
and another, there's
often this nomenclature
of whether you're doing
early fusion or late fusion.
And what people
usually mean by that
is, are you bringing
the modalities together
as soon as possible and then
running your processing forward
from there, or do you
process each information
stream separately and then bring
them together at the very end
when you actually need
to make a decision
about the state of the world
and your actions in it?
So I have to admit that
this framework doesn't
help me think about
this space too much,
but I've tried to map
onto these five things
where I think they fall.
And there's a range here
from super early fusion
to what I would think
of as late fusion
and everything in between.
So we'll see if you agree
with me as I go through it.
The first thing I'm
going to talk about
is learning joint
embedding spaces.
So a model that many of
you might be familiar with
is the CLIP approach for
combining the modalities
of image and text.
The primary idea here is to
do contrastive learning, where
you have two encoders,
an image encoder.
Let's see if my mouse shows up.
You have an image encoder
that pushes images down
into an embedding, and
you have a text encoder
that takes
corresponding captions
and pushes those down
into an embedding.
And the objective
for the model is
to make the embeddings for
corresponding image and text
pairs as similar as
possible, while pushing away
the representations
of mismatched pairs.
For example, the similarity
between the embedding
for image 2 and caption 1
should be as low as possible,
while increasing the similarity
between the embedding for image
1 and text 1.
And this is explicitly
trying to learn
a single joint
representation space where
if you pick a point
in that space,
there should be kind of an image
that corresponds to that point,
and also a text sample that
also corresponds to that point.
And that way you can translate
between the text modality
and the image modality.
You can see this
explicitly in the paper
on the right of this figure.
You can see that what they're
doing is taking an image,
figuring out what the
embedding of that image
is with the image encoder,
and then searching
over many possible text
inputs that will bring you
as close as possible to that
point in the representation
space.
So I would consider this
actually relatively late fusion,
because you're learning the
image encoder pretty much
separately from
the text encoder.
Those don't interact until
there's pressure through
the loss function to
make those embeddings as
similar as possible.
I would say, I don't want
to call it the grown up
version of this, but an
expanded version of this,
is the image bind approach.
And if people aren't
familiar with this,
it is still a contrastive
learning objective
between modalities.
But instead of just doing
images and captions,
it uses images as
kind of an anchor
and learns pairwise contrastive
between images and text, images
and depth maps,
images and audio.
And the underlying
objective here
is the same, that you want
a single representation
space where it doesn't
matter which modality you
came in through.
Once you know where you
are, you can back out
what all the modalities
should look like.
And in fact, in
this paper, they do
some interesting
demonstrations of that space
by doing things like
embedding space arithmetic,
or prompting with one
modality and seeing
where you fall in that
space on other modalities.
The other option that I
have done occasionally,
but I think is not popular
for technical reasons,
is super, super,
super early fusion
where you can just directly
concatenate raw inputs.
So consider if you
had, for example,
a 3D RGB color image and
you also had a depth image.
What you could do is
just staple on the depth
image as a fourth channel,
and then train a ConvNet,
or train your vision
transformer and pretend that you
had four channels all along.
That is a totally valid way
to incorporate information
from multiple modalities.
The reason that I think
it is not super popular
is it requires that there's
something to concatenate on.
So people typically will
first project raw inputs down
to tokens and then concatenate
token streams, which
I'll talk about in a second.
But if you want to
jump really, really,
really to the front of
that encoding stack,
sometimes you have your height
and width dimensions on images
line up and you can just
concatenate directly.
The third option that you
could do is cross-attention.
So now, we're getting much
more transformer-specific.
The idea here is you have
two token streams, one
from each modality.
In the example
from the Lu et al.
2019 paper, you have one token
stream that comes from images,
and then you also have
a second token stream
that comes from text.
So those are your
two modalities.
You can have as many
self-attention layers
as you want within each stream.
But then you can also have
these cross-attention layers,
which are shown here in the
diagram, where you're basically
giving each modality the
chance to be the primary.
The primary will
generate the keys--
or sorry, the queries in
the attention operation,
and the secondary stream will
provide the keys and values.
And because that is an
asymmetric procedure,
you will often see these
cross-attention layers
duplicated on either side
of the processing stream,
so that, in one
example, the images
get to provide the queries
and then the other side of it
the text stream gets
to provide the queries.
I broke this out just because
when I was first implementing
this, it was helpful
to think about,
but if you look at what
is actually happening
in an attention layer,
you have your input x,
you will have a linear
projection to your queries
Q, your keys K,
and your values V.
And then those go into your
scaled dot product attention
operator and then linear
projection and dropout.
All you're doing in a
cross-attention layer
is you're taking input
from another stream y,
and you're using that to
generate the keys and values,
but everything else stays as is.
This gives you a chance to
have the two information
streams mingle somewhere in
the middle of the network.
So I would call this
intermediate fusion,
depending which layers
you're doing it in.
The fourth option,
which I alluded
to when I was talking
about concatenation,
is you can just slap
tokens onto a stream.
I think one thing that has
really resonated with me as we
move into using transformers
in more and more domains,
the fact that everything is
just tokens all the way down
makes it really easy to add
more tokens to a sequence,
and they can come from other
modalities if you'd like.
One way that this
happens all the time,
but I think we
don't really think
of it as multimodal
learning, is if you
have, for example, a vision
transformer, you might add on.
In this case, you're
prepending a CLS token
that really is like--
you could think of
it as text, I guess,
because the class is
literally a text label.
But you have an
embedding for the text,
and that just goes
and participates
in the stream of
tokens and participates
in the self-attention
operations.
And there you go.
You've integrated a text
label with your image data.
The other place you
see this is actually
in the DALL-E 1 implementation.
So the way that this worked
is you have text tokens, which
are captions for images.
You also have image
tokens, which in this case
come from learning a
codebook with a discrete VAE.
And you concatenate on the image
tokens after the text tokens.
And then at inference time, you
can provide only the text tokens
and autoregressively predict
what the image tokens should be.
So again, you've solved
the multimodality problem
by first boiling everything
down into token space.
And then, once they're
tokens, your decoder
doesn't need to know
which ones are image
and which ones are text.
And finally, something
that we have increasingly
been using at Noetik is this
adaptive layer norm idea.
So I really like this figure.
This is from the diffusion
transformer paper.
What I like about
it is that they also
talk about two other things
I've already mentioned.
The middle column there
shows how you might
do this with cross-attention.
I guess I should back up
and say, in the diffusion
transformer case, the extra
modality you're feeding in
is a conditioning token.
You want to guide the diffusion
in a particular direction.
So you have some
text label and you
want that to interact
with the main transformer
block that is going to
be doing the diffusion.
So you could do that
with cross-attention,
which is shown here.
You could do it
with what is called
in this paper, in-context
conditioning, which is just
the concatenation approach.
You can actually see that here.
Concatenate on the sequence
dimension, as we just saw.
But the thing introduced
in this paper,
which is very parameter
efficient and cool that it
works, is you can take that
conditioning information
and use effectively a
linear layer to push it
into small scalar parameters.
So here, what they're doing
is predicting an alpha, beta
and gamma.
They actually
predict two triplets
of alpha, beta, gamma and
use those in the layer norm
operation.
So this is just
another way, as far
as I understand, to push
information from one modality
and have it steer or
influence or guide
what is happening
in the processing
of the primary sensory stream.
I have a little
code snippet here.
Probably not worth lingering
on, but it's just striking
how straightforward
this approach is.
Really, all that's happening is
you have a single linear layer
in here hiding after
a non-linearity,
and then you're using
that to determine
the parameters for shifting and
scaling operations in LayerNorm.
And this turns out to
be a very effective way
to get information about a
text-based conditioning label
into the image domain.
OK, this is a pretty good
place to pause and see
if anyone has any
questions before I move on.
Yeah, particularly when we
talk about the cross-attention,
can cross-attention
on LayerNorm, 1,
could be used as the other
LayerNorm as a linear reference?
Yeah, if I understand correctly.
I think you can.
And the thing that you
run into here, that's
both a blessing and a curse.
It's like you can do
pretty much anything.
At some point, if you think that
there's more useful processing
to do before you derive these
LayerNorm shift and scale
parameters, this doesn't
have to be a linear layer.
It can be an arbitrarily
complicated function.
It could be a
cross-attention layer
that is using the information
from two streams that way,
and then also doing a LayerNorm.
The question is, is it
parameter efficient,
does it work
empirically, and do you
have a good principled
reason to do it?
And I think often
that third thing
is missing in a lot
of these approaches,
which is just like,
yeah, it seems to work.
so we're going to roll with it.
Thank you.
Yeah.
Can you speak to
that complex level.
I mean, maybe on
a conceptual level
on why in a cancer
research space,
that transformer is important in
the sense that does it combine,
let's say an image of a
patient or let's say biopsy
and maybe the text
description of this.
So what makes transformers so
relevant for cancer research
in a bigger context?
Yeah.
So the question is,
why are transformers
important for cancer research?
And I think the answers could
have basically, two shapes.
One of them is if you format
your data and your task
properly, I think transformers
are both simpler to scale
and empirically scale better
than other approaches.
The second reason,
I would say is not
all data modalities are
amenable to other architectures.
So sometimes you
do have image data,
and I'll show examples
of that in a second.
Sometimes you have data that
looks a lot more like text,
and so you want to use the
approaches that have been
successful in modeling text.
And then the third
thing I would say
is that specifically
for multimodal learning,
it's extremely helpful to
be able to push everything
into token soup and bring it
back together however you want.
So it turns out that
transformers are just
a very good substrate
for combining
kind of arbitrarily
creative ideas
about how to integrate
various measurements,
but in a couple of
slides, I'll show
exactly what those
measurements are,
and I'll walk through
architectures we're using
to learn from patient data.
Cool?
OK, I will go ahead and do that.
So as a reminder, this is
kind of my mental model
for how things work in
the macroscopic world.
And I think the analogy
in the microscopic world
is, now we want to understand
the world of cancer biology
and the queries that we want
to pose to this world model
are not things like what happens
if I walk into a roundabout?
They are things like,
what will happen if I
give this drug to this patient?
Will the tumor go away or not?
And you want--
effectively a simulator
that can help you
answer those questions.
I will fill in
the question marks
momentarily about
what these sensors are
and what the data looks like.
But I want to put this
up front as our goal is
to take this world
modeling approach
and to build a system that we
can use to simulate answers
to clinically
relevant questions.
OK, this is my crash course
in cancer immunology.
I was talking to a card-carrying
immunologist this morning
and apologized for trying to
boil down their entire career
into a few bullet points.
So please know that this
is a gross simplification.
The basic idea behind
cancer immunotherapy
is that we know that in
some cases, [? deer ?]
immune system can detect
and destroy cancers.
But tumors are sneaky
and they evolve
to either hide from
the immune system
or to actively suppress
the immune system so
that the immune system can't do
its job and destroy the tumor.
The idea behind immunotherapy
as a type of treatment
is you want to basically get
rid of those immune evasion
mechanisms or the immune
suppression mechanisms,
and help reactivate immune
cells to help them do their job.
So you already have the
machinery in your body
to fight cancer, it's
just losing that fight,
and you want to find a
way to tip the scales so
that the immune system
can start winning.
The way that we do
that could have two
shapes, and we're interested
in both of them at Noetik.
One of them is you
just find new drugs
that no one has
thought of before.
But the other thing that I
was interested to learn when
I started working in
this space is actually
there's a lot of drugs
that have progressed
in various clinical trials, and
they fail because there's just
a mixed response.
For some patients they work
really well, for other patients,
they don't work at all.
And we don't have the right
way of targeting the right drug
to the right patient.
So for both of these, the
thing you would want is,
again, a world model
that can help you
simulate the answer
to the question.
Given what you know about the
world of this patient's biology,
if I take this action, does
the tumor go away or not?
So here's the oversimplified
schematic again of, you want
something that tells you,
given a patient's data,
you want to be able to
simulate kind of rapidly
a bunch of different
treatment options
and get a reasonable
prediction of whether they'll
be effective or ineffective.
So our approach to
this is, first, we
need to deploy our sensors
and collect a bunch of data.
This is a video of our lab up in
South San Francisco in action.
So what we do is we
get human lung tumor
specimens and a few other
tumors from a few other organs.
These numbers are also a little
bit outdated at this point,
but we source our tissue blocks.
We have a lab that
processes them.
We punch out these
cores from the tissue
that are about 1
millimeter in diameter.
So they're very tiny but
I'll show you in a second
that there's an unthinkable
amount of data packaged
in that small 1 millimeter core.
And then we will
basically put those
through four different
data processing pipelines
that I'll show you in a second.
One of those pipelines,
which is a fairly common one
to run on tissue samples, is
we collect these H&E images.
H&E has the benefit
of being relatively
cheap and easy to acquire,
and a lot of people have it.
So most hospitals
and research centers
are sitting on a ton of H&E.
There's a lot of public H&E.
And if you want to do machine
learning on biological data,
it basically looks
already like images,
so you kind of know
what to do with it.
It's like a three channel RGB
image that you can work with.
Technically, it's like
a two channel thing,
because there's two
elements of the stain,
but you can deconvolve
them if you want.
It's not super relevant
to the rest of this talk.
The other thing that we do
is, instead of just looking
at the gross morphology, which
is what you mostly get out
of this H&E stain, is we
have a 16-plex protein
immunofluorescence panel.
So that means that we're
able to detect proteins,
16 different kinds of
proteins, by designing
fluorescent antibodies
that bind to them.
And we can see the
composition of this tissue.
So in this pseudocolor
map what I'm showing
is green, our T-cells, which
are part of your immune system.
Blue is B-cells,
which is another part
of your immune system.
And then the red blob in
the middle is a tumor.
So we're able to go ask what's
actually in this sample.
This is kind of an RGB image
but with 16 channels instead
of three channels.
The other thing to
call out here is
you'll notice that the
white box has moved with us.
So these are spatially
aligned samples.
And if you remember what I was
saying about RGB and depth,
you might already be
thinking, oh, well,
you could just
staple these together
in the channel dimension and do
multimodal learning that way.
One of the cooler kinds of
data that we have is spatial
transcriptomics.
So on, again, these
exact same samples,
you'll see the white box
is moving with us again.
We are able to detect
in 1,000-plex panel.
So we're looking for 1,000
different genes worth of RNA
transcripts.
And those transcripts
are spatially localized.
So we don't have to boil
down the sample into soup
before feeding it in and asking
which RNA is in the sample.
We get an XY co-ordinate and--
well, it's really like
an XY by gene tuple
that tells us this gene has
RNA expressed at this location.
And you'll get anywhere
between a few thousand
to a few million
such transcripts
in just 1 millimeter
of data, which
I'll try to show in a second if
it doesn't crash my computer.
This data is very rich.
It's also very complicated.
It's also very expensive.
So collecting this
data is the hardest
and it's the thing that
the fewest people have.
In fact, on one of
the previous slides,
I had mentioned that we at
Noetik estimate that we have
well over 1% and probably
over 2% of the world's spatial
transcriptomics data
using this platform,
which is called CosMc's.
And the last thing we do
is genetic sequencing.
We do whole exome sequencing
of the patient's data
so we know if they have
genetic mutations that
could be relevant to
understanding their tumor
biology.
So this is the data
that lives out there.
And the question is, how are
we going to learn from it?
Before we do that, I just
want to talk a little bit more
about the spatial
transcriptomics data,
because it's so cool.
So these are what the raw
transcripts look like in 3D.
This is-- we do actually
detect them in X, Y and Z,
but the Z-plane is 4
micrometers, 4 microns.
So it's very, very thin.
It's effectively just XY.
And the colors here
are different genes.
I'm going to try to run a live
demo of just what this raw data
looks like, because it's a lot
of fun to play around with,
but there's an
overwhelming amount
of data jammed into this 1
millimeter diameter chunk
of tissue.
I promise this computer
is not underpowered.
It's just loading
11 million points.
So this is what it looks
like at the micro level.
You have this
incredibly rich tissue,
and we are actually
showing here one
of the first whole transcriptome
runs we've been able to do.
So instead of detecting
1,000 gene panel,
we're able to try to
detect over 18,000 genes.
And we ran out of colors
after the first 20
or So but you'll have
to take my word for it.
So what the colors denote here?
The colors are different genes.
Yeah.
OK.
I will spare my
computer from trying
to render that for too long.
Here's another example
from our 1,000-plex panel,
just to give you another sense
of the kind of data that we work
with.
So at the local scale, now we're
talking about tons of microns.
You have these highly
localized reads
of what RNA is being
transcribed where in the cell.
And I'll try to
render the labels,
but again, the plotting software
struggles a bit with it.
OK, that's kind of an aside.
I just think those data are
so cool that I like showing it
whenever I have the chance.
OK, so let me talk
about how we're
trying to model this data
and the kinds of world models
that we're trying to construct.
So we have thousands,
at this point,
over 10,000 cores from
different patients.
Each of those cores is one of
those 1 millimeter diameter
circles.
In each core there will
be thousands of cells,
and we can assign these
transcripts to cells
with a segmentation algorithm
to say, in a given cell,
you can count up how often do
you get a read of this gene CD3E
within the borders of a cell.
And So the data you get
is effectively tabular.
It's also very, very sparse.
Most cells don't
express most genes.
We're going to try to model
this so that we can simulate
things and ask,
well, does this tilt
the tumor immune
microenvironment in a more
or less favorable direction?
Our general approach is to
use masked autoencoders.
This ends up being a
transformer backbone.
The thing worth calling
out is that it's not
autoregressive
transformer processing,
so there's no real sequence
to the genes to care about.
It's more like masked
language modeling,
where what we'll do
is take the input,
we'll mask out
some of the tokens,
and we predict the
tokens we mask out.
I'll show on the next
slide what that actually
looks like operationally.
So if this is your input,
imagine this has 1,000 rows,
soon 18,000 rows.
You have every gene
and how often it
was detected in a single cell.
So the input is one cell here.
We have a tokenization
process that
assigns a token to each
combination of gene identity
and the expression level.
So you're encoding both how
much of that thing you have,
and also what the
identity of it is.
And then we do partial masking.
In our work, we tend to do
pretty aggressive masking.
So the number you
should have in your head
is like north of
90% of the tokens
are removed and replaced
with a learned mask token.
So almost everything is
removed from the sample
and the job of the model is to
predict the things we removed.
This is intentionally
a very hard task.
We want it to be basically
as difficult as possible
while still learning
the biology,
because if you are able
to do this, what it means
is that you're able to use a
very small amount of context
to infer, OK, well, I
see I have a lot of CD3.
I don't get to see
how much CD8 I have
because that got masked
out in the masking process.
So I have to GUESS based
on my knowledge of biology
from learning from this
data set, is it likely
that I express CD8, which would
make me a cytotoxic or a killer
T-cell if I express CD3,
which is kind of a more
generic marker for T-cells
that may or may not
be killer T-cells.
At inference time, what
you can do with this model
is provide a couple
of things that are not
masked, like two tokens
worth of information,
and then staple on a
bunch of mask tokens,
the other 998 genes
in this panel.
And then you can predict
everything that's masked out.
So you can say,
given that you're
conditioned on
knowing you are T-cell
and you're not a tumor, what
else do you think is happening?
And if you've learned
from this huge data set,
you might think maybe the best
you can do is say, well, OK,
what is the average
T-cell look like?
Because all I've told you is
you have this T-cell marker CD3,
and you're definitely
not a tumor cell,
because you're expressing
none of this keratin marker.
I don't want to say that
this model is boring.
There's a lot of interesting
stuff you can do with it,
but it's distinctly
not multimodal
and I promised
you multimodality.
So I'm going to keep going
with this background in mind
and tell you about one
model that we have gotten
a lot of leverage out
of, which is to say,
this task is very hard and
there's a lot of ambiguity.
And if you remember,
I was talking
about multimodality
as a way to resolve
ambiguity in predictions.
So one thing that
we do is we will
take the local
spatial neighborhood
of a cell, the one we're trying
to make predictions about.
We'll ask, who are your
eight nearest neighbors?
And we will force
the information
about what those eight nearest
neighbors are expressing
through a bottleneck.
That bottleneck is just
another transformer,
but it is required to
boil down basically
all of that rich spatial
context about what's
happening in the local
environment down into one token.
And then we use this
adaptive LayerNorm approach,
or we've tried the
append tokens thing.
We've tried cross-attention.
They all seem to work.
Some are just more
efficient than others.
And that feeds in as an
additional input to what
we refer to as the backbone.
So now, if you have a
prompt in your training
that's ambiguous, you
have a little bit of help,
because you might
say, well, I don't
know if I'm a killer T-cell or
not, but seven of my neighbors
are killer T-cells.
Maybe I'm also a killer
T-cell, and that should help
you do a little bit better.
And the thing that I should
have added here and forgot
is showing that if you're
just monitoring the training
loss of the backbone,
it really likes
having the spatial context.
It helps quite a lot in
lowering that loss curve.
Once you have a
model like that, you
can do very large scale
inference with it.
So what we will do is take
a real patient sample.
We'll pick a location
in that sample,
look up the eight
nearest neighbors,
and then we will ask the
model to do inference
with a specified prompt.
In this case, I'm telling
it, you are a killer T-cell.
You express these markers
for regular T-cells
and for cytotoxicity,
and I'm asking
it to predict the other
990 plus genes conditioned
on the spatial context.
And on the right, I'm going to
slowly build up at each position
here what the model
thinks is happening
for one such gene, IL7R.
And you will already
get a sense once this
starts to speed up, of how many
simulations we're doing here.
As of last week,
I think we had run
on the order of 6
billion virtual cell
simulations like this.
So we are able to ask basically
arbitrary queries about what
is happening in patient tissue
by saying, hypothetically,
if this cell type were in this
location in the patient tissue,
what do I think it's doing?
And to close the
loop in a second,
I'll tell you about
how you can do
counterfactual simulations
that will help you
think about potential drugs.
But for now, just
appreciating that once
you have this additional
input stream to the model,
you can pull out
a lot of richness
about what it's learned about
how spatial context affects
what is happening at
the single cell level.
We built a little
web UI that lets
you explore some of this data.
I won't spend too
long in it, but it
lets you pick a cell type, fly
around a real patient sample,
see what the cell identities
of those nearest neighbors
is, and then see how the model's
prediction of different genes
changes as you move
around the space.
So I could spend all day kind
of mucking around in this,
but it's public.
Feel free to poke around.
Let us know if you find
anything interesting that we
should turn into a drug.
Celleporter?
Yeah, the link is
celleporter.ai,
as we think of it as teleporting
cells around in patient data.
May I ask a question?
Sure.
So masking seems like a
really interesting approach
and strategy to apply.
Is that to narrow it down to
that one particular pathway?
Is [INAUDIBLE] 90% masking
so you can actually
trace every single one?
Is that the core
function of masking?
I think it buys us two things.
The first is that
at training time,
it makes the task
very, very hard so
that the only way
you could answer it
is by learning about
fundamental patient biology.
If you provided-- go
to the other extreme,
you provide 999 genes.
You only need to predict one.
You will probably
identify that, oh,
I can usually predict this
gene by the combination
of these other two.
The other thing
that it helps us do
is, I'll show this in
a second, but if you
train with a very high masking
ratio, at inference time,
you can bump the
masking ratio to 100%
and the model doesn't freak out.
It's like, oh, yeah, I'm used
to seeing almost nothing.
And then you can do
interesting things like, well,
what if I give you no
information about that center
cell and you only get to use
the local spatial context, which
is a mode we actually
operate in quite often.
Yeah.
OK, this is another
kind of thing
we would do with
these virtual cells.
So the thing that I
showed on this slide
is the surrounding
context is real data.
We go to a real location
and a real patient's tissue,
look at 8 nearest cells,
feed that expression in.
But the model doesn't
know what's real data
and what isn't, so you can go
create a synthetic neighborhood
and say, OK, I'm going to
start from the real data,
and I'm going to simulate
the effect of a drug
by knocking down a particular
target I'm interested in.
And say the neighborhood
is basically
the same, except that I've
removed a target of interest.
I've done a synthetic knockout
in the surrounding context,
and I want to know when
I do that knockout,
do I make this
hypothetical center
T-cell more or less likely
to be in tumor killing mode?
And that's what this
animation shows.
The gene identities
are redacted,
but the y-axis is the
increase in the production
or predicted production
of granzyme K, which
is part of the T-cells cytotoxic
arsenal for attacking tumors.
And we can do these simulations
for each of these 10,000 plus
patient samples for each of
the 1,000 genes in the panel.
And you start to see how,
with the right scale,
you can very quickly search over
hypotheses for what's happening
in the patient tissue.
Yeah?
How will this [INAUDIBLE] be
updated for 20,000 or 7000--
Yeah.
So maybe a year
or so [INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
Good question.
So the question is 8,000
patients worth of data enough
or do you need more?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
Could you augment
with synthetic data?
I think the answer is maybe.
I would say if you are staying
within a single indication,
like we often think about
non-small cell lung cancer,
it's possible 8,000 patients
covers the diversity
of different patient biology or
different modes that the tumor
might be using to escape
the immune system.
I think there are things you
could learn from expanding
to more indications,
different cancer
types and different organs
that could be generalizable,
or even back to non-small
cell lung cancer.
And So we are actively
collecting right now
more data and more
indications and more organs
to make sure we're not ignoring
a pocket of how the tumors might
be learning to evade
the immune system.
Can we generate theoretically
so that everything
would be able to assume
[INAUDIBLE] is the case for all
of us to have a sense
of [INAUDIBLE] scalable
[INAUDIBLE]?
Yeah.
I think there probably are ways
to generate synthetic data.
I'm not sure learning from
it directly would help.
If you're using a model that
has trained on real data,
I'm not sure if it's going to
do better when it's generating
its own synthetic
data, but there
are ways you can use
your own knowledge
about the biological
system to produce things
like these synthetic
neighborhoods
where you're saying, I'm going
to go make a targeted change
and then run inference and
see what the model thinks
will happen when I do a
very specific perturbation
in the data.
[INAUDIBLE]
Thanks.
OK.
The thing about this data
that I mentioned earlier
is it's expensive, and it's
rare, and it's hard to collect.
I also mentioned that this
H&E data is image-based,
it's pretty cheap, it's fairly
ubiquitous, a lot of people
have it.
And one thing that we've
been doing increasingly
is seeing if we can
use our model, which
we call OCTO in part informally,
because it kind of looks
like an octopus
with a bunch of arms
that sample different
modalities to just translate
from one to the other.
So now, we're back to
multimodality as translation.
The way that you do
this is take this model
that we're now familiar with.
And now, this diagram
should look very familiar,
except instead of
gene expression
data from the
local neighborhood,
we're passing in
the surrounding H&E
morphology of what is
happening local to that cell
in the patient's tissue.
We can only do this, because the
samples are spatially aligned
as precisely as they are.
And now the model gets to use
this additional input as help.
It's saying, I'm facing
ambiguity, what can I do?
Oh, well, I can look at
the morphology of the cells
around me and try to understand
if that makes me, for example,
a cytotoxic T-cell or not.
Once you've trained this model,
you can then go to full masking.
Just say, OK, I'm going to
effectively ablate the primary
input and just pass
in 1,000 mask tokens.
And now the only
thing the model can do
is use the local
spatial context to say,
well, I don't know
anything about what
the expression should be.
I have to use this
local context to try
to make a prediction
of what the gene
expression of a
hypothetical cell
at the center of that
spatial window is doing.
And because we've trained it
at a very high masking ratio,
the model is not totally
clueless about this.
And we were curious if it
makes reasonable predictions.
So what we will do
at inference time
is take one of these
H&E images, which again,
are fairly easy to acquire.
Pick a spatial window
and run the model forward
in inference mode
and say, OK, I'm
not going to tell you
anything about the expression
of the cell in this case,
because I don't have it.
We don't know what's going on.
There could be someone
sent me this H&E image
and they never ran
spatial transcriptomics.
The model will make a prediction
about what the expression of all
1,000 genes in our panel is
at the center of that spatial
window.
And here, it's giving me
some value for a keratin 19,
which is a tumor marker.
And you can just run this
as many times as you want.
So in practice, we'll
run this 1,000 times.
Yeah.
One question online is,
are you only predicting
the transcriptomics of
non-cancerous cells?
No.
We are predicting the
transcriptomics for every cell,
including immune cells,
tumor cells, fibroblasts,
stromal cells,
whatever's in the data.
Yeah.
So if you run this process
a few thousand times,
you get basically a prediction
heat map of where is it likely
that there's a tumor, because
you're asking the model
to predict one of the 1,000
things it's predicting at each
of these locations
is a tumor marker.
So here's the heat map you get.
And then, this is
now going back.
And for this core
we actually do have
cell typing from
transcriptomics data,
and the red dots are where
there's actually tumor.
And you can see
that the model is
predicting where there's tumor
markers pretty effectively.
I won't pretend this is perfect.
There are definitely examples
where it doesn't do a great job.
So here's another sample
that has a ton of B-cells.
That's the blue in this diagram.
And it does-- it mostly
predicts that there
isn't a lot of tumor marker,
which is mostly accurate.
There isn't a lot of
tumor in this sample,
but it's still missing the
few areas where there is.
But for other markers, even
within the same sample,
it's doing a very
good job of predicting
from just this
morphology image what
the expression of
various genes is.
And yeah, imagine 997 more
columns of this diagram and then
10,000 more slides
with other samples.
And that's how we're evaluating
the ability of this model
to do that translation
from the images
to the rich spatial
transcriptomics.
So essentially this
is what we call
the masking where the
[INAUDIBLE] images are cheap.
And So you train it on the
other set of images or picture,
and then you can generalize
on it [INAUDIBLE].
Right.
We're leveraging the fact
that we have the paired data
in-house, so we can teach the
model to do that translation.
And then, at inference
time, the model
is happy if you
mask everything out.
It'll just use
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
--your synthetic data, because
now you can see the other one
is readily available
to you concerning that.
And then you can have
better prediction.
Yeah, totally.
So the thing I'm going to show
on the next slide is actually--
I've been playing with ideas
for what would an interface look
like for, you have H&E data,
you don't have the ability
to generate spatial
transcriptomics.
You can imagine an interface
where someone uploads their own
H&E. You predict a full 1,000
dimensional panel of what
the expression is of a bunch
of different genes at every
location.
We know what different
gene programs look like,
and you can actually use
a large language model
to find for you common areas
where things are popping out
and descriptions of
what's happening.
So you get a fully
end-to-end automated.
You upload a sample, we predict
what the gene expression would
be in that sample,
and then you can
go explore the data,
talk with an LLM,
Explorer, whatever you want.
Ask questions about
it and eventually run
simulations in browser.
So cool.
OK.
So basically what
we have built here
is a system that
attempts to translate
relatively easy to acquire
data into rich patient
representations.
This is kind of a pretty PCA
projection of the first few
principal components of the
1,000 dimensional signal at each
location.
But what we will actually
do with that is then
each dot in the
diagram to the right
is one sample from one
patient, and we're embedding it
in a two dimensional space.
In this case, I think
we're using t-SNE,
and we're putting
patient samples together
if their predicted gene
expression profiles are similar.
And what I'm labeling by here is
actually the patient genetics.
So the model has no idea
about whether a patient has
a genetic mutation in
cancer driver mutations.
But it turns out that,
because the model has learned
patient biology, when you
cluster together predictions
from different
patients, the ones
that have common
genetic mutations
end up clustering in this space.
So you can recover
patient biology
starting, again, just
from this H&E image,
because we have trained this
model on a bunch of paired data
that has H&E and
spatial transcriptomics.
[INAUDIBLE] interesting
classification stuff.
Yeah, we spend a
lot of time asking
what the structure of this space
is telling us about the data.
I'm just going to give a quick
tour of another model that
will look familiar,
because it's using
similar masked autoencoding.
This is using that protein data.
So in this example, the model is
not predicting gene expression,
it's predicting protein images.
And we're feeding in the
other three modalities
as extra tokens.
So this is now not the adaptive
LayerNorm thing I mentioned.
It's just stapling on bonus
tokens into the token stream
and letting them interact with
the primary token stream, which
comes from these 16
channel protein images.
So H&E is the data that
you are able to create?
We--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
--also collect [INAUDIBLE].
We collect all of this.
All of it, OK.
Yeah.
So into this model, if I'm
creating a new data set,
given that earlier process,
can that become another input?
Yeah.
So you could only collect
H&E impute or predict
what the spatial transcriptomics
would have looked like if you
collected it, feed that in.
The question is, if that
helps you learn anything,
and I don't have an
answer to that yet.
We are exploring it but
it's an interesting idea.
OK.
So what we do in this space
is ask questions like, well,
how do we want to simulate
the effect of a drug?
The effect of a
drug simulated might
look like modifying the
spatial transcriptomics
data where you say this drug
suppresses this protein.
And So you could say
that the way that
would look in a spatial
transcriptomics data
is suppressing the leads of one
gene or a combination of genes.
And you're going to run
this counterfactual.
A what-if of, well, what
if I had applied that drug,
changed the spatial
transcriptomics
data in this way,
and run that forward
to a prediction of saying,
well, how does that change
the output of the model
trying to predict the protein
image on the other side?
And I have a small animation
showing how that might happen.
So this is a sample
from a patient.
The yellow here
are immune cells.
The pink is tumor.
Now, you can run two what-ifs.
In one what-if
simulation, you're
cranking up the expression
of this gene whose identity
is redacted here.
And in the other one,
you're suppressing
the activity of that gene.
So now I'm back to
creating synthetic data
on my multimodal input arms.
And I'm going to now run both
of those parallel universes
forward.
And what I'm looking
for is the readout
is one of these 16 channels
that's being predicted.
In this case, I'm looking for
a tumor immunogenicity marker
where higher would
indicate more favorable.
And you can see that this
simulation is telling us,
yeah, you should crank up the
expression of gene 1 if you can,
because it leads to a
more favorable outcome
on the other side.
So one way that we often
are using multimodal models
is to say we want this backbone
that makes predictions to tell
us what would change if we could
impart a delta or a modification
or a perturbation on another
one of the input streams.
So how do you go
[INAUDIBLE] there?
Well, if you're able to express
your hypothesis for what
a drug should do in the
input space of the model,
and you have a readout
on the other side of what
is good or bad,
then yeah, you could
compare multiple different
ideas and see which one looks
like it to be most effective.
Here are [INAUDIBLE]
of the [INAUDIBLE].
OK, I showed a relatively
small fraction of the research
that we're doing here.
But in general, we're
very open about sharing
the science we're doing.
So we have 3 blog posts up.
You can get to them
at noetil.ai/research.
This first one is about the
protein image-based models
that I just showed.
There's more detail on how
we're generating data in lab.
And then some of this new
spatial transcriptomics stuff
is in a more recent post.
OK.
I just have a couple
of more slides.
And then it looks like
we'll have a bit of time
for further questions.
One thing that we're
moving toward doing,
if you'll excuse kind of
the chaotic animation here,
is instead of trying to assign
these RNA detections to cells,
we're just going
straight to the raw data
and seeing what we
can do with that point
cloud of 10 million points that
my computer choked on earlier.
And So we're
training models that
are able to look at the
local spatial context
in this raw point cloud
of RNA transcripts
and predict what is going
to happen at many points
spatially in the sample.
So we're breaking free of
the need to think about cells
as the atomic unit of
simulating the biology
and going basically as close
to the raw data as we can get.
So this trajectory
in biology would not
drive through a sample like
this, but for a visualization,
I'm showing at
each position here
we're running one
inference step.
So I ran this model
a few thousand times,
moving this hypothetical
cell a few microns at a time,
and then simulating what the
readout would be of saying,
OK, well, when you're surrounded
by this cloud of transcripts,
you're probably also
seeing this cloud near you,
and this other cloud over there.
And So this is now the
kind of simulation engine
where basically
any hypothesis you
have about what a
drug might be doing
or what's happening
in patient biology.
If this model has really learned
about the world of the patient's
biology, you should be able to
get a reasonable simulation out
on the other side.
So in summary-- oh,
I had one more slide.
I noticed last week was on the
biology of a large language
model, which is a
paper I really liked.
So I have a tongue
in cheek slide
on the biology of a large
multimodal model for biology,
which is just a little teaser.
I don't have a ton of
time to get into it,
but we've been doing some
interpretability research
on these models to
try to understand
what it is they have learned
about the patient biology.
So we've used things
like sparse autoencoders
to pull out consistent
themes that keep popping out
in the data, and have used
those to build interfaces
for biologists at the company
to basically do things
like automatic semantic
segmentation with text labels
from identifying persistent
assistant concepts that
keep appearing in the data set.
So again, this is starting
from just the agent.
So you upload agent in, you
get back semantic segmentation
with the different
parts of the sample
and what's happening
in each of them.
This is basically my last
slide, which is just saying,
I hope one thing I've
communicated today
is that this is just
a big playground.
There's a ton of data.
There's a ton of ways you
can try to combine that data.
And especially in
biology, you have
data spanning many
spatial scales,
many levels of abstraction,
and also many modalities.
So we talked today about
really the three of them,
the imaging, the
immunofluorescence and RNA
sequencing.
There's more to
be done in looking
at the patient genotyping.
There's immunohistochemistry.
The field of omics keeps
getting bigger and bigger.
And so the question that
I think we have to solve,
and that I don't think has a
concrete answer yet is, what
do you do with all of this?
How do you build
a world model that
incorporates all of
this information,
and how do you craft your
training tasks, your information
bottlenecks, and
your fusion points
so that you're forcing
a model to really learn
real patient biology that
is specific to each patient?
And I won't pretend to
have the answer today.
We don't know.
We're trying a bunch
of stuff and throwing
a lot of ideas at
the wall and then
having a lot of fun
playing with it.
But I just want to leave
people with the idea
that there's just a ton
of things to try here,
and I think it's going to be a
very exciting few years ahead.
So with that, I'll now
fill in the picture.
This is our idea for building a
world model for tumor biology,
and I'll save the rest of
the time for questions.
[APPLAUSE]
In the space of [INAUDIBLE],
there's a lot of--
there's HIPAA, there's a lot
of privacy protection laws
that prevent, let's say, for
researchers like you to probably
have access to real data.
So my question is,
let's say if data
is localized at
each hospital, how
do you see the future
of research in this area
can leverage the vast
data set in the siloed
in different hospitals
so that this can advance,
so to speak to a place that can
be diffused into a health space?
Yeah, that's a very
important question.
I think there are a
few different answers.
One of them is open sourcing
of methods that you could say,
we aren't going to ask you to
send us your confidential data,
but we're going to tell you
how you can run it yourself.
There's probably also
ways that I'm not
familiar with to just secure
end-to-point base scans
and say we're going
to, as a service,
process this data
for you and we'll be
compliant with the privacy
regulations about how
to get the data from your
hospital to the servers
and back.
It's very much not
my area of expertise,
so I don't know exactly
what that looks like,
but I imagine someone is
thinking very hard about it.
And I think the third
thing is partnership,
that you can always have
a hospital or research
institution say, we want access
to a bunch of these models.
We're going to go into
a formal partnership
where we have access to
the compute and the models
that you've trained, and
we're going to work together
to run these samples
so that it isn't
just kind of an arbitrary like,
yeah, email us your H&E data
and we'll process it.
Yeah.
Oh, amazing.
I just can't wait to see if it
can be expanded to larger data
sets than just 8,000 patients.
My other question is, I
know cells and molecules
and proteins, there are so many
models beginning to happen.
Are you able to leverage a
lot of the AlphaFold models
that already exist in the
protein layer data set
and also exosomes.
In fact, the two
new things which
are getting to be
very interesting
is bioelectrics, which is
beginning to be another Holy
Grail, not just cells.
Is there any way
to can also capture
that data set in early
experimentation out of the four,
but I'd like two other layers?
Yeah.
And exosomes, particularly
the communication channel,
that can add value.
Yeah, I think that's
a great question.
One thing I've come to believe
is that most forms of data
can be jammed into these
frameworks fairly easily.
And the question
is, empirically,
does that help with
anything or not?
And I don't know, but I
think to be totally candid,
we're at a place in research
where we can try a lot of stuff
very quickly and see what helps
us make better predictions.
In some cases, I
think what we're
doing is probably upstream
of models like AlphaFold,
where once we have run
our simulations and said,
well, OK, our world model is
telling us if you could only
make reality look
like this, then
this patient would
respond to treatment.
Then we might still have
a challenge of, OK, well,
what is the actual
pharmacological path by which we
get there?
And then you might need
to engage with something
at the molecular level.
So yeah, I think it's
possible that one
of the big challenges
that I'm thinking about
is indeed, how do you integrate
across these spatial scales?
And we've tried some
stuff, but we have not
spanned this entire range
yet in a single model.
So is your approach
right now research
to start with patient
data first or just
to a broad predictive
model, then
I can figure out later
who the patient is?
Because there's so much
of the early prediction
that's happening where
you're not a patient yet.
Right.
There are no marker,
there's no tumor yet,
but you're able to predict.
Yeah.
Long short.
Yeah, right now we are
working from patient data.
And one limitation
of that data set,
which I think is what
you're pointing out,
is that healthy
people don't get parts
of their bodies removed and sent
to hospitals or to research.
So really the
thing we would want
in a world model is
evidence of, well,
what does it look
like when everything
is working, when
there's no tumor, when
the immune system has identified
a threat and eliminated it?
And we just don't,
because what we're getting
are these snapshots
of a battlefield.
And if we're lucky,
we will see a snapshot
and then find out that patient
received some treatment
and responded well to it.
But we're missing
probably the vast majority
of the system operating in
normal operational mode.
And I don't see an immediate
way out of that challenge other
than acknowledging
it and recognizing
that what we're
trying to do is learn
as much as we can
about the snapshots
we get of disease
state and learn
from that as a starting point.
With a broad institute has some
really interesting projects
where they're just taking
dead tumor specimens
and they're just doing a bunch
of computational modeling.
It's really cool to see
if that can be integrated
with this [INAUDIBLE].
Yeah, our attitude is very
much like, as much data
as we can get, we're going
to throw it at this thing.
I'm grateful.
Thank you.
Any other questions?
I have a quick question.
So is Noetik just
a model company?
Do you outsource the drug
discovery to other people
and just let them use your
service as a platform,
or how does it work?
No, we are effectively
as full stack as it gets.
We generate our
data in-house, we
do the machine
learning in-house,
and then we have biologists
and immunologists in-house.
I didn't talk about this at all,
but we have an in vivo platform
with mice where you can actually
go test hypotheses about saying,
here's a mouse model for
this patient population.
We think that this
drug will be effective.
Let's go test it.
So we, right now, actually
do not provide any of these.
Even if you wanted to pay me
today to go use one of these,
I don't have an API
endpoint for you,
but we are using
these internally
to do drug discovery and
basic discovery every day.
So the model is like a
lower latency version,
and then the mouse is just to--
so you do most of your
testing with the model,
I assume, and then the
mouse is just a few--
after you do the initial
filtering with the AI model,
or how does that work?
Yeah, so the model can
tell you two things.
In the best case,
it tells you, hey,
you should go try
this drug in mice.
We don't pretend
that this model is
going to understand all of the
complex biology that happens
when you administer a drug.
So you still need to go to
that in vivo test case and say,
is this actually working
to get rid of tumor?
The other thing the models tell
us is maybe there's already
a drug people have tried,
but they're trying it
in the wrong population.
They're enrolling too
broad of a clinical trial,
because they don't
know that actually,
this small sliver
of the patient space
is the one that's going to
respond well to your drug.
And So we are using the
model in that capacity
to give us ideas for things
to try in our in vivo platform
or to re-examine clinical data
and see if we can understand why
clinical trials have
failed, where other people
are kind of shrugging and
going, well, I don't know,
10 people were totally
cured, but the other 190
weren't, and we don't know why.
That makes sense.
So is the end game to completely
replace clinical trials or--
I don't know.
I mean, maybe in
many, many years.
I think ultimately
safety and efficacy
proven out in humans will
need to happen at some point.
If anything, I would assume that
the earlier part of that funnel
is going to be increasingly
done synthetically,
that maybe we say you
can, in some cases,
skip a mouse model if you have
a very clear mechanism of action
and you want to go
straight to checking
for safety and efficacy.
Thanks.
Yeah, thank you.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
--scenarios of
simulations to test
with many different
combinations.
I'm wondering how you
narrow it down to prioritize
which one to test first.
Yeah, that's a
fantastic question.
So I think of what
we're doing is
like, let's say you had a really
good world model, a simulator
of the world.
Even in the macroscopic
case, you still
need an agent to tell you
what is worth simulating.
You can't just try
things at random.
And I think there's two
promising things here.
One of them is you still have
subject matter experts that
say, oh, great, you've
given me a perfect simulator
of patient biology.
I know the first
30 things I'm going
to try because I'm familiar
with the things that have
been considered in this space.
We have hypotheses for
how the tumor is evading
the immune system,
and we want to go
see if we can disrupt those.
The other thing
that I don't know
how much weight I want
to put behind right now,
but would be a little
foolish to dismiss,
is that we have these LLMs now
that are trained on basically
the entirety of
scientific literature,
know about a bunch of studies.
And if they have access
to effectively tool use
and say, OK, what experiments
do you want to run?
And start thinking about virtual
scientists or AI scientist
agents that are
trying to decide,
this is the next
experiment I would do.
And maybe at some point,
you close the loop
and you say, great, we're
going to go run that experiment
and we'll be back to you
tomorrow and then tell me
the next thing to try.
But either way,
you need somebody
who's familiar with the
domain, whether that's
an LLM or a scientist,
to make the decisions
about how to use the simulator.
Got it, thanks.
Yeah, thank you.
Yeah, so I know your grand
vision is to cure cancer.
Do you have some thoughts on
cancer prevention, probably
vaccines and stuff like that?
Yeah, that is a good question.
I'm not sure I have a fantastic
answer about how are we thinking
about cancer prevention.
It relates to this
problem of, we
don't have healthy
data to look at.
And if there isn't an indicator
right now in the clinic of,
yeah, you look healthy
today, but we're still
going to go biopsy this
and send it off and fit you
into this framework.
Then I think you're
going to be limited
in what you can do
about simulating
the patient biology of patients
that, right now, are totally
asymptomatic.
I could imagine that changing.
I mean, it's possible
that data acquisition
is going to be broad
enough and cheap enough
that it is just routine to
have a little bit of H&E taken.
And maybe there is
information in the latent
space of this model
that says, yeah,
this looks like it's
over in this part
of the patient distribution.
Maybe we keep an eye on this
patient over the next few years.
Same question.
Great.
I have a follow-up question.
Google scientist, AlphaFold,
and all this stuff.
Yesterday, Microsoft released
a co-pilot or semi autopilot
for science discovery tool.
I'm very curious how we can
run a billion experiments
autonomously.
Maybe instead of modeling
a world scenario, maybe
model a person as an agent
and figure out what drugs
could potentially cure the--
context, we just lost someone
like two weeks ago to cancer.
So this is a very
big thing for me.
How do we prevent or cure
in the intermediate cancer?
So that's the way I'm
thinking about where
agents and science intersect.
Yeah, I have a
few thoughts here.
I'm not sure how
coherent they are.
One of them is I am not sure
yet that speed and scale is
the bottleneck on running
these simulations.
I have not also
seen an example yet
of an agent come up with a
really brilliant experiment
that our scientists
didn't write down
in the first four
minutes of thinking
about how to use this thing.
That doesn't mean I'm
not optimistic about it.
I think these systems
are going to get better.
And if anything, I have been
wrong every time on saying like,
yeah, that's five years away.
And then five months later it
turns out that we can do it.
So I would like to
remain optimistic
that we're going to be able
to frame these problems,
integrate things like
tool use in a way
that does allow agents to go
run a bunch of experiments.
And then for us, we probably
still go test those out in mice
and then think about
them in that capacity.
But yeah, it's a very
interesting direction
to think about.
[APPLAUSE]
OK, give another hand to Misha
for the very interesting talk.
Yeah, so you'll notice
this talk was different
from a lot of the more
recent talks or work,
just focusing more on LLMs.
But I think this is a very
important space and an area,
application area, where
machine learning and AI can
make a lot of impact and save
the world, change the world,
positively impact the
world and save lives.
So we should
definitely encourage
more work for machine
learning and AI
for this area of cancer research
and healthcare in general.